It's easy to get into home roasting
though, right?Because you can do that on
anything. I mean, you can really do it
with a frying pan.
It is an immensely labor-intensive
process to grow coffee.
So we started this three years and two
days ago.
This is the seed of a cherry.
Mycotoxins are toxins that are produced
by yeast and fungi. So
I I leased this roaster from higher
grounds, really dialing in a roast
and really being able to execute it the
way I want it.
You don't want to do this really fast,
because most of the coffee in the rest of
the world is all bread from a tiny
handful of beans. My name's Luke
Cizek, and I'm the founder and roaster at
Lab Notes Coffee.
The coffee originated in Ethiopia. It's
since been spread, you know, throughout
the whole world. But originally a lot of
European countries, I want to say like
the Dutch and the French really started
like exporting coffee out of Ethiopia
into Europe. But they really wanted to
maintain their monopoly and not let other
people grow coffee. So there were export
rules saying all the beans had to be
boiled before they left the country so
that nobody could actually use the plant
these seeds and and grow their own
coffee. Most of the
coffee that's available in countries
outside of Africa are all
descendants from literally one handful of
coffee that a Dutch person
smuggled out in the 1500s. I believe it
was 1500s, somewhere around there. And at
the time, you know, doing so, I believe
the penalty was death. Like you could get
killed for smuggling out
unboiled coffee. It
is an immensely labor intensive process
to grow coffee, right?The cherries,
generally speaking, are picked by hand
when ripe. Every cherry has two coffee
beans in it. So think about how many
coffee beans go into your One Cup of
coffee that you drink in the morning. So,
so much work goes into growing that
plant, picking all of the cherries, then
processing the cherries and ending with a
green coffee that someone can roast and.
And I think just general awareness about
that is important. People need to realize
that that the people growing the coffee
are the ones really doing all the work.
You know, think about anything else you
buy and how much, how big it is and how
much it costs you. To be able to get a
pound of green coffee for under $2,
that's wild.
This is the seed of a cherry. So there's
a whole process for getting the beans
out of the cherry. There's naturally
processed, which historically has been my
my favorite. You're less likely to have
bad things happen, like the coffee end up
with a bunch of mycotoxins. So mycotoxins
are toxins that are produced by yeast and
fungi. Some of the like stated effects of
those include things like jitteriness,
stuff that people actually attribute to
to caffeine. And these are things that
are are going to be more prominent in
those cheaper coffees, right?Where the
they really are not processed well in
terms of what happens after harvesting.
They're not good for your body. They
don't make you feel good. They don't add
to your coffee drinking experience is the
type of coffee where you drink a lot of
it and it makes you feel kind of tired
and you wonder what's wrong with this
coffee. And then like 6 hours later,
you're like, oh yeah, I'm awake and like
I'm not going to be able to sleep
tonight. Guess there was caffeine in
there after all. But the way you
feel right out of the gate is,
I believe, a good indicator of whether or
not mycotoxin.
I think I sort of feel like coffee right
now is going through what beer did, you
know, a few, a decade or a few decades
ago. I feel like there's always more
room. Granted, the the roasters seem to
be getting smaller and smaller, but I
think that's really awesome. So there's,
you know, a handful of local roasters. I
love to drink all their coffees and I'm
really glad they all exist. I think it's
a lot of fun to to try other people's
coffees. So from my point of view, there
is a lot of room. I guess if your goal is
world domination, you know, there's
there's already a lot of really big
coffee companies out there. So you got to
really bring something unique if you're
going to take over. But it's neat that
the coffee roasting world is slowly
becoming more and more collaborative.
Whereas before it was all super
secretive, people didn't want to talk
about how they roasted or share roast
profiles or really get into the details
of, you know, their personal beliefs on
roasting theory. It's all like a hidden
black box of this is our our proprietary
thing and we're not going to tell anybody
about it. So I think it's really cool
that, you know, that people are talking
about it more openly. I think even if
you're doing something that works really
well, it it's why not share that with
other people and let them try to do that
too. Really elevate, you know, all of the
coffee if you really think what you're
doing is is the best way to do it.
So I have a full-time job that I do
normally and that's really what pays our
bills. We do this because we love doing
it. So we started this three
years and two days ago was our our
launch date. So we've done this in a
really like low capital expenditure
way, right. We we lease time on somebody
else's roaster. We've actually been able
to keep our expenses low enough that
we can keep our purchases on
0 interest introductory APR credit
cards and pay them off and open a new one
as needed. And so far that has
worked 100% for us. And
we know that won't work forever and that
at some point we'll actually take out a
business loan. But it's been really,
really helpful for kind of getting our
foot in the door. So I was a
patron here for years before I ever even
thought of starting a coffee company or
trying to see if I could lease time on
this particular roaster. So roasters are
really, really expensive relative to what
they make. So there's a small roaster. I
roast 5 pounds at a time on it. A used
roaster like this is like $15,000.
Margins in coffee are pretty small, so it
really take a long time to pay that off.
And it also requires a commercial space
to operate it in. So having no roaster or
space for the roaster, leasing really
worked out well. Initially we thought
maybe at some point we'd buy a roaster
and operate it out of our house. The more
I learned about all of this, the less
likely I think that actually is that
we'll be able to get the right permitting
for a bigger roaster on a residence. It's
easy to get into home roasting though,
right?Because you can do that on
anything. I mean, you can really do it
with a frying pan. You can get a $30
popcorn popper and you can use that.
The home roaster I used for my sample
roasting was about $400. So again, it's
is a hobby. It's very, it's something you
can really get into pretty easily.
This computer makes its own graph, but
there's no way that I'm aware of at least
to get the data out of this graph. So
every 30 seconds I record the
temperature, rate of change, total amount
of time. And then lastly, the final
temperature all play a role. So this
orange line is the temperature change
overtime. Blue line is the actual
temperature of the beans. Getting there
in 11 verse 15 minutes will affect the
roast. So I just entered the temperatures
and it outputs a rate of rise in degrees
per minute. The amount of time you spend
in the last 10 degrees will dramatically
affect the roast. And this is the type of
curve that we're shooting for where it
peaks relatively early and then we have a
continuous decline after that point. A
different ending temperature of 1 degree.
You can taste that. It would be so much
harder to do stuff consistently
if I wasn't taking the time to do it on
this computer. Over
roasting is much more common in terms
of the whole world of coffee. There's a
lot of coffee companies whose lightest
coffee is darker than our darkest coffee.
If that's the cup of coffee you like,
that's I have no problem with that. But
for me that. I now see those as really
not showing the true flavor of the coffee
and really just having like a lot of
roasty or ashy flavors. And
a lot of people are kind of brought into
coffee thinking that's what it's supposed
to be, you know, like. Like in a a
century class at a culinary school, they
will teach you bitter with coffee. Like
coffee is your example for bitter. But
it's amazing. I mean, there is really
just about any fruit and berry you can
imagine. And there's a lot of chocolatey
flavors. There can be buttery and
caramelly flavors. There can be earthy
flavors. There can be different types of
spiced flavors in there. You can detect
as a nuanced flavor in a brewed
coffee that is literally just coffee. So
we're gonna brew some coffee in a French
press. First step is
grinding it at the right size. This is
just the regular Capresso coffee grinder
that you can buy for your house. I like
to use the quart, the finest of the
coarse grind sizes. Generally
speaking, for French press and cold brew,
you want to go with a coarse grind.
For any new coffee I brew, I always start
with a water to coffee ratio of
16 to one by weight. I always weigh
everything. If you can weigh everything,
you'll be able to make the most
consistent cup of coffee. So for a normal
French press, just any French press you
would buy at a store, you can generally
brew 880 grams of
water. It's just a little bit less than a
liter. For that, I'll
use
55 grams of coffee.
I always like to use water that's 200
degrees Fahrenheit. Some people like to
go up to 205 or as low as 195. I
feel like 200 is is the perfect starting
temperature to use. So I target a total
brew time in a French press of five
minutes. When I'm adding the water this
way through a relatively slow pour
kettle, that means I'll set a timer once
I'm done adding the water for four
minutes. If I was using a different
kettle that adds the water all at once
real quick, I would set the timer for
five minutes. And usually about halfway
through, I'll stop and just kind of
swirl the coffee, make sure all the
grounds are saturated. Now set a timer
for four minutes.
All right, time to press the coffee.
You don't want to do this really
fast. That extra pressure will
extract more out of the coffee, generally
in a bad way.
I would encourage everybody to pursue
their passion. What is what is it that's
easier to do besides what you're
interested in, right. So, so if there's
something you're interested in that,
yeah, you should look into how you can
work that into your life. And there's
usually a way to do it regardless of your
situation, right. And to use our coffee
situation as the example, you know, not
having to buy a coffee shop or
buy a roaster in order to even start a
company and it and it didn't start it
starting a company, you know, it started
it. I just would like to roast more
coffee. and doing a lot of roasting
at home. Anybody who, I guess, feels like
they can't pursue those things that they
they really want to do, I would challenge
them to to look at it differently and
find a way. I think I think there's
always a way to be able to make it
happen. So we're going to make a pour
over in a Chemex.
While the coffee is grinding, you can wet
out your filter. That way you don't have
any dry spots where water will not flow
through and extract through the coffee
properly. First step is to do a
bloom with the coffee, do an initial
wetting out of the grounds and let
everything become saturated in water.
General rule of thumb is to use three
times the mass of water is the mass of
beans you have, so it's three times the
weight of that 40 grams of coffee the
bloom will. Actually give you a sweeter
coffee. It'll give you a better
extraction. So what's happening now is
all the grounds are becoming saturated
with that initial water and there's some
initial like off gassing that is
happening from the beans. The idea for
this is to pour near the center. You
don't want to pour around the outer edge.
Pouring around the outer edge will cause
the water to kind of bypass your grounds
and just go straight into the bottom of
the vessel. You don't want to fill it up
all the way simultaneously. You don't
want to let it dry out entirely. So I'll
continue to add water and little pulses
like this till we get to 640 grams.
Really dialing in a roast and really
being able to execute it the way I want
it, right?So there's just that like
personal satisfaction there with it going
the way I want. But then feedback from
people is a huge piece too. Like the
making something that other people enjoy
is. I like a lot more than I
would have guessed. That That really
does bring me a lot of joy. Just being
able to do something that I love and for
it to also be something someone else
really loves is is
my favorite part of it.